<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bogdan Dicher</title>
    <link>http://bdicher.me/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Bogdan Dicher</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 15:13:57 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://bdicher.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>May Athena make you wise(er than I am)!</title>
      <link>http://bdicher.me/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 15:13:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bdicher.me/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It took some time, but the blog section of the website is finally up &amp;ndash; albeit as a practice run. I will finalise it in a week or so, but until then I may as well add some content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided to make the blog something of an aside to the website, mainly because I don&amp;rsquo;t trust myself to keep to a regular blogging schedule. However, I have big plans. Apart from my review of Nissim Francez&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Proof-theoretic semantics&lt;/em&gt;, the first instalment of which will go up tomorrow, here&amp;rsquo;s what else I have in store for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, I have been thinking about &lt;em&gt;immigration and refugees&lt;/em&gt; and re-read Dummett&amp;rsquo;s book (&lt;em&gt;On immigration and refugees&lt;/em&gt;). (Incidentally, this is the only book on the topic I have ever read, so blogging about this is gonna a kind of &amp;lsquo;amateurs-gone-bonkers&amp;rsquo; affair.) I will report these thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have a blog post written in Romanian about a couple (?) of years ago. I wrote it when the &amp;lsquo;refugees crisis&amp;rsquo; hit its peak. At that time, it was hard to tell who had the more disgusting attitude: the Romanian government or the Romanian intelligentsia. What was clear is that they were equally dumb, so I thought even my amateuresque intervention may help. The post was never published. I sent it to a friend who was running a nice (leftist) blogging platform, but he said pass, ostensibly because it was too abstract. It is true that it was developing a philosophical argument of sorts and I reckon you can&amp;rsquo;t go more abstract than this if you want to write words, not formulae. So I&amp;rsquo;ll try to post that here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this should keep me busy for a couple of weeks, provided I&amp;rsquo;ll find the time/energy to get any busier than I already am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tout!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>