<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Bogdan Dicher</title>
    <link>http://bdicher.me/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Bogdan Dicher</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 10:31:20 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://bdicher.me/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Rebetiko (I)</title>
      <link>http://bdicher.me/post/rebetika/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 10:31:20 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bdicher.me/post/rebetika/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My friends know (and are duly horrified by the fact) that I have a bit of a &lt;em&gt;faiblesse&lt;/em&gt; for a rather strange musical genre: &lt;em&gt;rebetiko&lt;/em&gt;.
Lately, some rebetika made it back into my daily playlists.
So in this post I&amp;rsquo;ll begin to tell you the story of my encounter with rebetiko. I&amp;rsquo;ll do it backwards: today I&amp;rsquo;m going to tell you where I got; in a future post I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you where I started from. (If you can&amp;rsquo;t wait that long, click &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/fqW89c4vbBA?list=PLd2ehAknsn53rKqokJO5afKSRiPTfc1Jt&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for a clue.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rebetiko is a Greek musical genre (perhaps the work &amp;lsquo;tradition&amp;rsquo; describes it better) whose roots are in the musical practice of the suburban (and often interlope) Greek world at the turn of the 20th century. What I like about it, at least in its pre-classical and classical periods (that&amp;rsquo;s before and, respectively, during the 30s) is the transparency of its eclectic nature. Rebetika draw heavily on the Oriental (Asian) musical traditions. Indeed, initially, they are &lt;em&gt;oriental&lt;/em&gt; songs.
Here&amp;rsquo;s a sample: Marika Papagika&amp;rsquo;s 1919 recording of &lt;em&gt;Smyrneiko Minore&lt;/em&gt;. (Funny, it was recorded in New York!)

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Ux_whsihlM0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s a modern take on the song, by Savina Yannatou:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/M4ir0rK_ci8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s great fun to &lt;em&gt;listen&lt;/em&gt; how this music evolves as it blends with the European tradition - or at least with the European tradition of the Southern Balkans.
For instance, this is Vamvakaris&amp;rsquo; take on the traditional zeibekiko of Asia Minor in the 30s, during the Piraeus period of rebetika:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/if4SkbfCSvI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the years pass rebetika become more and more &lt;em&gt;European&lt;/em&gt;. Listen, for instance, to Mpellou (probably the greatest, wonderful&lt;em&gt;est&lt;/em&gt;, magnificent&lt;em&gt;est&lt;/em&gt; voice in the past, present and future of rebetiko) singing &lt;em&gt;Sinefiasmeni kiriaki&lt;/em&gt;:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/QR03kMVUZ9k&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(If you want to learn more about rebetiko, there&amp;rsquo;s a decent Wikipedia &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rebetiko&#34;&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; about it. Even better is Gail Holst&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Road-Rembetika-sub-culture-sorrow-hashish/dp/9607120078&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Road to rembetika&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nissim Francez&#39;s &#39;Proof-theoretic semantics&#39; (I)</title>
      <link>http://bdicher.me/post/francez1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 22:16:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bdicher.me/post/francez1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;preamble&#34;&gt;Preamble&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sharing an office with Francesco Paoli and, ever since I arrived in
Cagliari (that was in February), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.technion.ac.il/~francez/&#34;&gt;Nissim
Francez’s&lt;/a&gt; book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.collegepublications.co.uk/logic/?00031&#34;&gt;Proof-theoretic
semantics&lt;/a&gt; was always
of Francesco’s desk. Okay, this is the wrong way of putting it; for one
thing, I’ve read it. What I mean is that the book was never re-shelved.
That’s a good faith for a book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular book deserves aplenty a friendly review and I have
planned to write one for some time now, but I never quite got to doing
so. This (i.e., training myself to keep a regular blog) is as good as
any an excuse to finally take some steps in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-review&#34;&gt;The review&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This review will come up in three instalments. The first (which is
already overdue according to the schedule announced in the very first
post) is an overview of the first part of the book; the second is a
discussion of several problematic philosophical arguments in the book;
the third and final instalment is an overview and discussion of the
second part of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is a practice run for the blog, I won’t bother with the
niceties one usually puts in a positive review. I’ll save that for the
official review. Instead, I’ll just say it outright here: I really like
the book. You too should like it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-first-instalment-overview-of-the-first-part&#34;&gt;The first instalment: Overview of the first part&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francez’s book is, to date, the only extensive monograph on
proof-theoretic semantics – i.e., the branch of logical inferentialism
inaugurated by Gentzen and subsequently developed by Prawitz, Dummett,
and others. (There is a twist here: Francez attempts to apply those
ideas to fragments of the natural language. This twist occupies the
second part of the book and it is the topic of the third part of this
review. However, I must confess that for me the best bits are in the
first part.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Introduction’ cursorily explores some of the philosophical
underpinnings of logical inferentialism in its proof-theoretic guise.
This is pretty standard stuff; Francez does little to elaborate on the
finer points of the matter. Nevertheless, the newcomer, even if
embarking from Philosophy station, may find some worthwhile exploring
paths here. I am more excited by the fifth section of the Introduction,
‘Natural-deduction proof-systems’. (I hate these hyphens.) This is a
systematic and very careful presentation of natural deduction in
Gentzen’s tree format. Everything is introduced by precise definitions
and clear examples. It’s great to have it at hand, especially since it
is the kind of stuff that I can’t stand writing. The chapter ends with a
section on the idea of natural deduction rules as meaning conferring.
Again, this is pretty straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of the book, ‘Proof-theoretic semantics in logic’
consists of five chapters. Chapter 2 presents some familiar logics
(minimal, intuitionist, classical, relevant; it also contains a brief
subsection on modal logic). This is just enough for making the book
self-contained, but one will not gain much knowledge of these logics
from here. The presentation is clear and illuminating; the pace is
pleasantly alert. Moreover, it already touches on central issues in the
development of proof-theoretic semantics. For instance, the section on
classical logic (2.2) is organised around the troubles generated by
negation via double negation elimination, the law of the excluded middle
and ‘indirect proof’ (i.e., classical &lt;em&gt;reductio ad absurdum&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third chapter (‘The basis of acceptability of ND-rules as meaning
conferring’) unfolds the drama of proof-theoretic semantics. About half
of the chapter is occupied by the discussion of &lt;em&gt;harmony&lt;/em&gt;. Recall that
this is a term introduced by Dummett to designate the match of strength
between the introduction and elimination rules for a constant. In turn,
this means that the rules for that constant are well-behaved. Or, to put
it slightly differently, it marks the success of the rules in defining a
coherent (logical) concept. (I’ll say more about harmony in the second
part of the review.) Francez discusses in detail three formal accounts
of harmony – intrinsic harmony, harmony in form, and symmetric harmony.
(Again, I will discuss these in more detail in the second part of this
review.) These are related to each other as well as to other concepts in
the same ballpark, specifically, normalisability and conservativeness.
The presentation is clear and easy to follow, especially if one is
comfortable with the logician’s/mathemathician’s habbit of breaking the
prose into designated environments. Alas, Thomas Mann and other
aesthetes have no reason to fear competition as far as style is
concerned. The second part of the chapter looks at the logics introduced
previously and checks whether their rules are harmonious. You know the
story: intuitionist logic is the winner; the other competitors appeal
the decision. It is well known that classical logic doesn’t pass muster
when it is formulated in SET:FMLA (i.e., when the formulation allows the
use of many premises but restricts the number of conclusions to one).
The solution to this problem is postponed for the subsequent chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4 tackles the problem of harmonising classical logic. Francez
considers the two main strategies: changing the framework and,
respectively, adopting a bilateralist perspective. The change of
framework amounts to switching to (what is usually called) a
multiple-conclusion consequence relation. I am rather excited by Francez
treating here the extra complication brought about by the possibility of
formulating multiple-conclusion natural deduction calculi with either
additive or with multiplicative rules. This topic deserves a lot more
attention than it has previously received in the literature and
Francez’s discussion of it is a welcome step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second strategy is to move from rules dealing only with assertion to
rules dealing with both assertion and denial. Francez discusses in some
detail Rumfitt-style bilateralism and provides a very nice account of
intrinsic harmony in bilateral systems. The final section of the chapter
surveys briefly ‘alternative conceptions of harmony justifying
[c]lassical [l]ogic’. One of these relies on the adoption of
‘impure’ rules. Such rules mention in their schematic formulation more
than one logical constant. I am rather baffled by Francez’s ‘own
position’ which is that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As long as the goal is the justification of Classical Logic (which
anyway contains disjunction), I find the arguments acceptable.
Furthermore, I find the general use of impure ND-rules acceptable for
the justification of &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; logic containing all the operators
mentioned in the impure rules. However, when the goal is the
(schematic) definition of negation, when added to an &lt;em&gt;arbitrary&lt;/em&gt;
object language […] I find the use of impure rules for defining
negation unacceptable. After all, harmony (here achieved via the use
of impure rules) is not a goal by itself – it only serves to rule out
“bad” definitions that do not satisfy the more immediate demands of
purity and separability. (p. 180)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a hard time wrapping my head around why - at least on the picture
of harmony preferred by Francez - the conditions for the correct
definition of a connective (here negation) may be overridden by whatever
happens in a certain logic, such as it containing another connective (in
this case disjunction). Besides, what is this goal, of justifying
classical logic, if not the goal of showing that its connectives are
harmonious? It may be that I am misunderstanding something here. But I
classify Francez’s intrinsic harmony as an account that is aims at
locality. That is, one that aims to characterise harmony only in terms
of properties of introduction/elimination rules for a constant,
&lt;em&gt;independently&lt;/em&gt; of what else happens in the logic under consideration.
This makes his conclusion very strange. (Locality is an aim which I
myself find misguided, but that is another question.) I will say more
about this in the second part of the review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The penultimate chapter in Part I is entitled ‘Proof-theoretic semantic
values’. This is a very interesting development, if one that I am not
feeling too confident in judging. Francez develops what is essentially a
theory of ‘grounds’ (in Prawitz’s sense). Grounds receive a precise
formal definition (p. 185) and their theory is pushed up to defining, in
a remarkably simple way, proof-theoretic logical consequence. There is a
wealth of stuff to think about in this chapter, whether one is provoked
by the idea of ‘reifying’ proof-theoretic meanings or tempted to explore
further Francez’s suggestion that his results ‘can be seen as fully in
concert with Dosen’s characterisation of connectives as internalizing
structural properties’. (This is an idiosyncratic selection. Read the
chapter and you’ll find other interesting stuff.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final chapter in this part, ‘Other developments’, surveys , as
you’ve guessed, &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; topics in proof-theoretic semantics. It goes
over Schroeder-Heister style higher order rules (which discharge
derivations, not only formulae), validity concepts in proof-theoretic
semantics, the sequent calculus as a backgground formalism for
developing proof-theoretic semantics and reductive harmony – a
harmony-based approach to what Dummett called first and second degree
justification of logical laws. I don’t really understand how the
material is organised in this chapter. Section 6.2., ‘Validity of
Arguments’, is 12 lines long; it is followed by two sections, entitled,
respectively, ‘Model-theoretic validity’ (6.3) and ‘Proof-theoretic
validity’ (6.4). The first is brief and largely recapitulative; the
second is longer and meatier. For instance, it includes a 6 pages long
subsection on Schroeder-Heister’s theory of ‘definitional reasoning’. I
am not quite sure what goes on here. This is definitely not how I would
have organised the same material. Despite this, it is worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>May Athena make you wise(er than I am)!</title>
      <link>http://bdicher.me/post/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 22:16:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bdicher.me/post/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;===&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took some time, but the blog section of the website is finally up –
albeit as a practice run. I will finalise it in a week or so, but until
then I may as well add some content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided to make the blog something of an aside to the website,
mainly because I don’t trust myself to keep to a regular blogging
schedule. However, I have big plans. Apart from my review of Nissim
Francez’s &lt;em&gt;Proof-theoretic semantics&lt;/em&gt;, the first instalment of which
will go up tomorrow, here’s what else I have in store for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, I have been thinking about &lt;em&gt;immigration and refugees&lt;/em&gt; and
re-read Dummett’s book (&lt;em&gt;On immigration and refugees&lt;/em&gt;). (Incidentally,
this is the only book on the topic I have ever read, so blogging about
this is gonna be a kind of ‘amateurs-gone-bonkers’ affair.) I will
report these thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have a blog post written in Romanian about a couple (?) of years
ago. I wrote it when the ‘refugees crisis’ hit its peak. At that time,
it was hard to tell who had the more disgusting attitude: the Romanian
government or the Romanian intelligentsia. What was clear is that they
were equally dumb, so I thought even my amateuresque intervention may
help. The post was never published. I sent it to a friend who was
running a nice (leftist) blogging platform, but he said pass, ostensibly
because it was too abstract. It is true that it was developing a
philosophical argument of sorts and I reckon you can’t go more abstract
than this if you want to write words, not formulae. So I’ll try to post
that here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this should keep me busy for a couple of weeks, provided I’ll find
the time/energy to get any busier than I already am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tout!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>